Register of the I. William Zartman collection
Hoover Institution Archives
I. William Zartman collection
1956-1970
94018
Hoover Institution Archives
12 manuscript boxes (4.8 linear feet)
The I. William Zartman collection consists of research materials on Africa compiled by Zartman in the 1950s and 1960s. Comprised of clippings, news dispatches, and serial issues, the collection documents political developments and economic conditions in a number of African states, especially those in West and Central Africa.
Zartman, I. William, collector
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1994.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical note
Biographical note
1952 M.A., Johns Hopkins University
1956 Ph.D, Yale University
1960-1965 Professor, University of South Carolina
1963 Author, Government and Politics in Northern Africa
1964 Author, Morocco: Problems of New Power
1965-1980 Professor, New York University
1966 Author, International Relations in the New Africa
1973 Author, Man, State, and Society in the Contemporary Maghrib
1980- Professor, Johns Hopkins University
1982 Author, The Practical Negotiator
1985 Author, Ripe for Resolution: Conflict and Intervention in Africa
2008 Author, Negotiation and Conflict Management: Essays on Theory and Practice
2010 Author, Understanding Life in the Borderlands: Boundaries in Depth and in Motion
Scope and Content of Collection
The I. William Zartman collection consists of research materials on Africa compiled by Zartman in the 1950s and 1960s. Comprised of clippings, news dispatches, and serial issues, the collection documents political developments and economic conditions in a number of African states, especially those in West and Central Africa. There is a considerable amount of information in the collection about the Nigerian civil war in the 1960s, which involved conflict between the Nigerian government and the breakaway state of Biafra. There are also significant materials on Cameroon; Congo (Brazzaville) and Congo (Kinshasa/Léopoldville); and the role of the United Nations in Africa. The materials are in English and French.
Africa--Economic conditions.; Africa--Politics and government.; Africa--Social conditions.
- Research materials relating to Africa, 1956-1970
  - Burundi, 1962-1969
    - 1962-1969 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - 1965-1967 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Cameroon, 1956-1969
    - 1956-1968 (Box-folder 1: 3)
    - 1958 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1959 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 1: 6-9)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 1: 10-11)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 2: 2-3)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Central African Republic, 1958-1969
    - 1958 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 2: 8-9)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - 1965-1969 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 1967-1969 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Commerce and agriculture, 1960-1968
    - 1960 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 3: 4)
    - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Communications and transportation, 1960-1968
    - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 3: 9)
    - 1960-1968 (Box-folder 3: 10)
    - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 3: 11)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 3: 12)
    - 1967-1968 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Communism, 1956-1968
    - 1956-1963 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - 1958-1964 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 4: 3)
    - 1965-1967 (Box-folder 4: 4)
    - 1966-1968 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Conferences and regional organizations, 1958-1968
    - 1958-1961 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - 1959-1963 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - 1964-1968 (Box-folder 4: 8)
    - 1965-1966 (Box-folder 4: 9)
    - 1967-1968 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Congo (Brazzaville), 1958-1969
    - 1958-1962 (Box-folder 4: 11)
    - 1959-1965 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - 1961-1964 (Box-folder 5: 2)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 5: 3)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - 1966-1968 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - 1966-1969 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Congo (Kinshasa/Léopoldville), 1961-1969
    - 1961-1964 (Box-folder 5: 8)
    - 1962-1969 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 5: 10-12)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 6: 1-4)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 6: 5)
    - 1968-1969 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Dahomey, 1960 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Equatorial Guinea, 1960-1968 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Gabon, 1958-1968
    - 1958-1960 (Box-folder 6: 9)
    - 1958-1968 (Box-folder 6: 10)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 6: 11)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - 1961-1962 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    - 1967-1968 (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Liberia, 1958-1967
    - 1958-1967 (Box-folder 7: 6)
    - 1961-1966 (Box-folder 7: 7)
    - 1965-1967 (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Nigeria, 1956-1969
    - 1956-1959 (Box-folder 7: 9)
    - 1959-1960 (Box-folder 7: 10)
    - 1960-1962 (Box-folder 7: 11)
    - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 7: 12)
    - 1963-1965 (Box-folder 7: 13)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 7: 14)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 7: 15-16)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 8: 3-5)
    - 1967-1968 (Box-folder 8: 6)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 8: 7-11)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 9: 1-3)
  - Oil, 1955-1968
    - 1955-1963 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - 1961-1968 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - 1964-1968 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - Relations between Africa and Asia, 1960-1968
    - 1960-1964 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 9: 8-9)
    - 1966-1968 (Box-folder 9: 10)
  - Rwanda, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 9: 11)
  - Sierra Leone, 1957-1968
    - 1957-1968 (Box-folder 9: 12)
    - 1960-1968 (Box-folder 9: 13)
  - Students, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Togo, 1956-1968
    - 1956-1966 (Box-folder 10: 2)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 10: 3-4)
    - 1961-1964 (Box-folder 10: 5)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 10: 6)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 10: 7)
    - 1967-1968 (Box-folder 10: 8)
  - United Nations, 1960-1969
    - 1960 (Box-folder 10: 9-10)
    - 1961 (Box-folder 10: 11)
    - 1962-1969 (Box-folder 10: 12)
    - 1964 (Box-folder 10: 13)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 10: 14)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 11: 2-4)
    - 1967 (Box-folder 11: 5)
    - 1968 (Box-folder 11: 6)
  - Upper Volta, 1958-1969
    - 1958-1959 (Box-folder 11: 7)
    - 1959-1960 (Box-folder 11: 8)
    - 1959-1969 (Box-folder 11: 9)
    - 1960 (Box-folder 11: 10-11)
    - 1961-1962 (Box-folder 11: 12)
    - 1961-1964 (Box-folder 12: 1)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 12: 2)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 12: 3)
    - 1967-1968 (Box-folder 12: 4)
  - Zambia, 1964-1970
    - 1964-1970 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - 1965 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - 1966 (Box-folder 12: 7-8)
    - 1967-1968 (Box-folder 12: 9)